{"tossups": [{"question": "Early in their history, this people displaced the Quapaw, Mosopelea, and the Tutelo and also defeated the Neutral Nation. The missionary Isaac Jogues, one of the North American Martyrs, was killed by this people and they later allied with the British in the Covenant Chain. 50 people of this group were sent to Marseilles as galley slaves after being captured at Fort Frontenac. In 1684, this people met with the colony of Virginia about use of the (*) Great Warpath. The woman Jigonhsasee helped to found this coalition with Dekanawidah, and these people would later fight the French in the Beaver Wars. For 10 points, name this group of Native American tribes led by Joseph Brant and Hiawatha.", "answer": "Iroquois Confederacy/League (prompt on the member tribes: Mohawk, Oneida, Onondaga, Cayuga, Seneca, or Tuscarora)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Iroquois Confederacy/League</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Iroquois Confederacy/League"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "prompt on the member tribes: Mohawk, Oneida, Onondaga, Cayuga, Seneca, or Tuscarora"}, {"question": "The historian Marcus Paterculus claimed that Arminius sent a king of this people the head of Publius Varus after the Battle of Teutoberg Forest, but that king forwarded the head to Augustus. A different king of this people, Ballomar, led them to victory over Rome at Carnontum and Opitergium. Queen Fritigil of this people corresponded with Ambrose of Milan, leading to their conversion to Christianity and their submission to Roman rule. This people were the first hostile force to enter Italy in nearly 300 years when they besieged (*) Aquileia around 170 CE. The Meditations were begun on a campaign against this people. For 10 points, identify this Germanic people who fought a series of wars against Rome during the rule of Marcus Aurelius.", "answer": "Marcomanni (prompt on Suebi)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Marcomanni</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Marcomanni"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "prompt on Suebi"}, {"question": "Many of the shipwrecked and wounded passengers of a ship named after a leader of this kingdom were killed in the Banka Island Massacre. The cession of this kingdom to the British was opposed by the group Rukun 13. Several uprisings of the Iban people against this kingdom were led by Rentap. The second ruler of this kingdom constructed the Astana Palace as a wedding gift for his wife. In 1945, the Japanese returned this kingdom\u2019s territory on the HMAS Kapunda in its capital Kuching. The first ruler of this kingdom encouraged fellow (*) Englishman Alfred Russell Wallace to conduct research in his state. Given as a reward in 1841 to James Brooke from the Sultan of Brunei for help in suppressing a rebellion, for 10 points, name this kingdom of northern Borneo ruled by the White Rajahs.", "answer": "Kingdom of Sarawak", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Kingdom of Sarawak</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Kingdom of Sarawak"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This man\u2019s entry into his country\u2019s capital was lined with flower petals after circumnavigating an enemy army. At Catlett\u2019s Station, this man overran Gen. John Pope\u2019s camp and took his uniform. This general failed to destroy the wooden bridge over Conococheague Creek because of false reports that it was made of iron during the Chambersburg Raid. Alfred Pleasanton defeated this general with a dawn raid at the (*) Battle of Brandy Station, the largest predominantly cavalry battle on American soil, and his inability to inform Gen. Ewell of Union positions contributed to the outcome of the Battle of Gettysburg. For 10 points, name this Confederate cavalry officer with an acronymic name.", "answer": "J. E. B. Stuart (or James Ewell Brown Stuart)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>J. E. B. Stuart</u></b>", "acceptable": ["J. E. B. Stuart"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "or James Ewell Brown Stuart"}, {"question": "One of these actions was opposed by Henry John Stedman Cotton, a former governor of one of the affected areas, who also led the campaign to remove Bampfylde Fuller from an office gained from this action. Huseyn Suhrawardy created an unused proposal that would have avoided the potentially dire economic consequences of one of these actions. During the second of these events, the capital of the region affected was the scene of mass rioting on Direct Action Day. The first of these actions led to the construction of Curzon Hall as a seat of governance in (*) Dhaka. These actions occurred in a non-Punjab province to make governance easier by separating Hindu- and Muslim-majority areas. For 10 points, what were these actions that divided a region of eastern South Asia, setting the stage for the later creation of Bangladesh?", "answer": "partitions of Bengal (accept synonyms for \u201cpartition\u201d; prompt on partition of India, but not Indian independence)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>partitions of Bengal</u></b>", "acceptable": ["partitions of Bengal"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept synonyms for \u201cpartition\u201d; prompt on partition of India, but not Indian independence"}, {"question": "This emperor raised the salary of soldiers to 675 denarii on the deathbed advice of his father, who said that he only needed to mind the army and not the general population. After an inconclusive campaign in the Agri Decumates region, he was given the surname Alemannicus. This emperor pretended to agree to marry the daughter of Artabanus V, but murdered her and her wedding party when they arrived at his camp. According to Cassius Dio, this emperor granted (*) citizenship to all freemen throughout the empire for the purpose of increasing the tax base. This man executed his wife and young daughter soon upon his accession and had his brother murdered in the arms of their mother, Julia Domna. Supposedly assassinated while urinating, for 10 points, name this brother of Geta and second Severan emperor.", "answer": "Caracalla", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Caracalla</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Caracalla"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Orson Squire Fowler, the primary popularizer of the octagon house, was an important proponent of this discipline in America. George Combe, author of The Constitution of Man, defended this study against Sir William Hamilton after the latter attacked it in 1826-27 in Edinburgh. F\u00e9lix Voisin founded a school in France that applied four separate curricula based on classifications made using this discipline. Paul Bouts combined this discipline with graphology and (*) personality typology to create psychognomy. This discipline was influential on Cesare Lombroso\u2019s theory of atavism and it could purportedly be used to identify criminals with only the use of calipers. For 10 points, what was this pseudoscientific discipline that claimed that the mind and personality were expressed through the shape and size of the skull?", "answer": "phrenology", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>phrenology</u></b>", "acceptable": ["phrenology"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": " One leader of this state sold the lead tiles off a palace, pawned the Crown of Thorns, and used his son as collateral on a loan to postpone bankruptcy. Mysia officially came under the control of this state after the first Treaty of Nymphaeum. The capital of this state was captured by only 800 men led by the general Alexios Strategopoulos of Nicaea. This state lost to Tsar Kaloyan at the 1205 Battle of (*) Adrianople. This state was established after its founders made a deal with Enrico Dandolo which required them to capture the city of Zara. Ended by the accession of Michael VIII Palaeologus, for 10 points, name this Crusader state established after the 1204 sack of Constantinople.", "answer": "Latin Empire of Constantinople (or Empire of Romania or Imperium Romaniae)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Latin Empire of Constantinople</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Latin Empire of Constantinople"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "or Empire of Romania or Imperium Romaniae"}, {"question": "The development of nixtamalization was an important development in the use of this commodity, as it prevents, among other problems, kwashiorkor. This commodity\u2019s historic spread has been correlated with the extinction of Epioblasma mussels. This commodity was represented as curls emanating from the foreheads of gods or in speech bubbles in Mayan iconography. This commodity was important for supplications at the main temple of Chav\u00edn de Hu\u00e1ntar because it was used to produce (*) chicha. This commodity was the first planted and tallest of the Three Sisters. This crop was developed from the grass teosinte and was ground between a mano and a metate to make the meal for tortillas. For 10 points, identify this crop, a staple of Pre-Columbian civilizations and the Midwest.", "answer": "maize or corn", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>maize or corn</u></b>", "acceptable": ["maize or corn"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A famous complex in this city was its primary funerary location until around the accession of Siyaj (\u201csee-YAHKH\u201d) K\u2019ak\u2019 and was connected to the North Acropolis via a sakbe. This city\u2019s ruling dynasty was overthrown in 378 CE by the forces of a ruler known in modern times by his name glyph Spearthrower Owl. With nine, this city contains the largest number of twin-pyramid complexes in Mesoamerica. This city was defeated by its rival Calakmul and its ally Caracol in 562 CE, an event now used to separate the Early and Late Classic Periods. Yik\u2019in Chan Kawiil constructed this city\u2019s (*) Temple IV, which is currently the tallest pre-Columbian structure in the Americas. For ten points, name this dominant city of the Maya lowlands home to the Lost World Complex, now in Guatemala\u2019s Pet\u00e9n department.", "answer": "Tikal (accept Yax (\u201cyahsh\u201d) Mutul or Yax Mutal)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Tikal</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Tikal"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Yax (\u201cyahsh\u201d"}, {"question": "The German Fountain was built outside of this place to commemorate a visit from Kaiser Wilhelm II. Later in its existence, this place was the site of tzykanion events. This nonreligious place contained a Kathisma at its eastern end above which was an art gallery. This place contains a bronze monument moved from Delphi that commemorated the Battle of Plataea (*), the Serpent Column. The Horses of St. Mark originally graced this place. An event that began in this place destroyed the second Hagia Sophia and saw the participation of the Blues and Greens. For 10 points, what is this starting point of the Nika Riots, a horse track in the Byzantine capital?", "answer": "Hippodrome of Constantinople", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Hippodrome of Constantinople</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Hippodrome of Constantinople"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "After defeating an enemy army, a holder of this non-Bulgar position apocryphally made a cup out of the skull of the general Atoc and drums from the skin of Atoc\u2019s brother Hango. One man in this position supposedly visited the \u201cfire belt\u201d and \u201couter belt\u201d islands on balsa rafts after defeating the Chimor people. Another holder of this position was named crown prince over his older brother Urco after a battle in which people claimed that stones had raised themselves to fight on his side to defeat a (*) Chanka army. After losing the Saksaywaman fort, a holder of this position founded a short-lived successor state based at Vilcabamba. The first person to hold this title was believed to be the son of the sun god Inti. For 10 points, identify this position held by Manco Capac, Pachacuti, and Atahualpa.", "answer": "Sapa Inca (or emperor of the Inca or any other answer that suggests the person ruling the Inca)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Sapa Inca</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Sapa Inca"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "or emperor of the Inca or any other answer that suggests the person ruling the Inca"}, {"question": "While a military officer in Shaanxi, this ruler took bribes and drank excessively so as to deflect any rumors of him having imperial ambitions. Before reaching his highest post, this man implied fealty to fellow rebel Li Mi; understandably, Li Mi was disappointed when this man later appointed him his Minister of Feasts. This ruler\u2019s ascent to power was greatly aided by an army independently raised by his daughter Princess Pingyang, which she led to several victories. This ruler\u2019s son was victorious at a nonfictional Battle of Hulao in which he received the support of the nearby Shaolin Monastery. This emperor was succeeded by his (*) second son after that son had his brothers assassinated in the Xuanwu Gate Incident. For 10 points, who was this father of Emperor Taizong and founder of the Tang Dynasty?", "answer": "Emperor Gaozu of Tang (accept Li Yuan or Shude; do not accept Emperor Gaozu of Han)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Emperor Gaozu of Tang</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Emperor Gaozu of Tang"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Li Yuan or Shude; do not accept Emperor Gaozu of Han"}, {"question": "Descriptive answer acceptable The controversial Younger Dryas Impact hypothesis suggests that a comet or air burst ended the first widespread archaeological culture to develop after this process. This process is dated, in part, to the distribution of Y-chromosome Haplogroup\u2013Q from its original homeland. Evidence of large fauna on Haida Gwaii and other islands supports the idea that this process may have occurred by sea. Pollen stratigraphy in Elikchan Lake describes a period of cooling that may have initiated this process, perhaps by causing a migration of (*) big game out of Siberia. The sites of Monte Verde and Buttermilk Creek challenge the long-held \u201cClovis-first\u201d hypothesis for the dating of this process. This process likely ended with the submergence of Beringia under the ocean. For 10 points, identify this process in which people came to inhabit the New World.", "answer": "settlement of the Americas (accept any answer that suggests people settling either/both North or South America prior to the", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>settlement of the Americas</u></b>", "acceptable": ["settlement of the Americas"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Eneko Aritza founded a kingdom comprised largely of people of this ethnic group in the 9th century. The largest city in the homeland of this people saw fighting between two prominent families in the War of the Bands. In 2015, this people signed a treaty officially ending centuries-old hostilities with Iceland. Merchants of this ethnic group monopolized trade with Venezuela during the mid-18th century A general of this ethnicity (*), Tomas Zumalakarregi, organized units called aduaneros during the First Carlist War. A town in this people\u2019s home region was bombed by the Condor Legion, an action immortalized in a cubist painting. For 10 points, identify these isolate-language speaking people of northern Spain and southern France.", "answer": "Basques (accept Vascos or Euskaldunak)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Basques</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Basques"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Vascos or Euskaldunak"}, {"question": "The patron saint of this modern country is often honored with the painting of erect phalluses on rural homes, referencing his \u201cFlaming Thunderbolt of Wisdom\u201d with which he apocryphally brought enlightenment to 5,000 women. Following the death of the first Shabdrung, this country established the offices of Desi and Je Khanpo to run secular and religious affairs respectively. This modern country defeated an attacking army by sheer luck when a gunpowder store blew up much of the invading army as they were looting this country\u2019s palace in the Battle of the Five Lamas. This modern country\u2019s dual administration system ended with the appointing of the first (*) Druk Gyalpo, or \u201cDragon King\u201d, Ugyen Wangchuk. For 10 points, identify this Himalayan kingdom famous for measuring Gross National Happiness.", "answer": "Bhutan", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Bhutan</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Bhutan"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "108 troops from this country held off 1500-2500 Vietnamese troops at the Battle of Long Tan. Soldiers from this country in WWI were praised for their \u201clarrikinism\u201d. Operation Slipper was the name of this country\u2019s operations in the war in Afghanistan. This country fielded cavalry units called Bushmen\u2019s Contingents in the Second Boer War. This country provided the bulk of Allied troops in the (*) Kokoda Track Campaign, preventing the Japanese from taking Port Moresby. This country\u2019s army led the peacekeeping mission following the independence of East Timor. For 10 points, this is what country that comprised the other half of the ANZAC with New Zealand?", "answer": "Australia", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Australia</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Australia"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This ruler supposedly sent two long-winded female ambassadors to drag out negotiations with rebellious nobles so as to buy time to build an army and catch them off guard. This ruler made the largest offer to ransom the True Cross after it was taken from Christian hands at the Battle of Hattin. This monarch publicized the drunkenness and \u201csodomy\u201d of Yuri Bogolyubsky who then made two failed coup attempts. This ruler is allegorized as Nestan-Darejan and Tinatin in the epic poem (*) The Knight in the Panther\u2019s Skin. This woman married the Alan prince David Soslan, who, along with generals Zakare and Ivane Mkhargrdzeli, campaigned against Shirvan, the Sultanate of R\u00fbm, and Armenia to make her kingdom the most powerful in the Caucasus. For 10 points, name this \u201cQueen of Kings\u201d who brought the Kingdom of Georgia to its political and cultural apogee.", "answer": "Tamar the Great (or Tamar of Georgia or Holy Righteous King Tamar; accept answers with either \u201cking\u201d or \u201cqueen\u201d because both terms are used)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Tamar the Great</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Tamar the Great"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "or Tamar of Georgia or Holy Righteous King Tamar; accept answers with either \u201cking\u201d or \u201cqueen\u201d because both terms are used"}, {"question": "One account of this man tells that Genghis Khan demanded to marry his daughter, but he said that he\u2019d rather see her burned alive than marry him. The meeting of Otto of Freising and Hugh of Jabala led to one of the first written accounts of his rule. This ruler was supposedly prevented from assisting the Europeans in the Second Crusade by the flooding of the Tigris. A letter from this man to the kings of Europe, later proved a forgery, says that his realm contains (*) centaurs, pygmies, and giant birds larger than horses. The conversion of many of the Kerait tribe to Nestorianism and the Mongol invasions of the Islamic world helped place his kingdom in northern or central Asia, but by the 16th century, Ethiopia was firmly believed to be this man\u2019s home. For 10 points, identify this mythical Christian king of the Orient, a popular legend in Europe from the 12th to 17th centuries.", "answer": "Prester John", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Prester John</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Prester John"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In the Talmud, Emperor Hadrian asks a rabbi to summon a massive one of these animals from the Bei Ilai Forest, but has the rabbi send it back after the animal destroys the walls of Rome, causes pregnant women to miscarry, and knocks out the teeth of Roman men, all from miles away. A famous emblem bearing one of these animals and the sun is first attested on the coinage of the Seljuk sultan Kaykhusraw II. A people named for these animals originate in the voyage of Prince (*) Vijaya, an event depicted in the Ajanta Caves. A duke with an epithet taken from these animals was the cousin of Frederick Barbarossa and founded Munich. A Malay prince founded a city named for one of these animals he saw on an island, a misnomer because he probably saw a tiger. For 10 points, identify these big cats from which Singapore derives its name.", "category": "History"}], "bonuses": []}